Guide to the Edward Dahlberg Papers M1551
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Edward Dahlberg Papers
Bulk, 1960-1977
Circa 1960-1977
M1551
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
8.0 Linear feet 12 manuscript boxes, 3 flat boxes
The papers document Dahlberg's writing career and personal life during the 1960s and 1970s.
Dahlberg, Edward, 1900-1977.
Other Finding Aids
Irving Rosenthal papers, M1550
Acquisition Information
Accession number: 2006-325 This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in December 2006.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in Five series:
Series I. Personal
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Professional
Series IV. Photographs
Series V. Clippings
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains correspondence, typescripts, photographs, periodicals, clippings, and ephemera. Included in the collection are typescripts for The Olive of Minerva; or, The Comedy of a Cuckold, (1976) and typescripts for the Crowell anthology, Bottom Dogs; From Flushing to Calvary; Those who Perish: and Hitherto Unpublished and Uncollected Works (1976). Other materials in the collection include unpublished typescript portions of The Carnal Myth (1968), The Confessions of Edward Dahlberg (1971), and extensive notes for miscellaneous works. The collection also contains incoming correspondence from a variety of prominent literary figures, as well as a few outgoing letters and drafts of letters by Dahlberg.
Biography
Edward Dahlberg, American writer of fiction, poetry, and criticism, was born in Boston in 1900. After a tumultuous early childhood, he was placed by his mother in the Jewish Orphan Asylum in Cleveland, where he remained until 1917. Dahlberg then joined the army and later worked as a day laborer while wandering the American West. In 1921, he enrolled at the University of California, Berkeley, where he majored in philosophy and anthropology, before transferring to Columbia University to complete his degree.
Dahlberg moved to Europe in 1926 and became part of the expatriate group of American writers living in Paris. In 1929, he published his first novel, Bottom Dogs, based on his childhood experiences at the orphanage and his travels in the American West. After the publication of Bottom Dogs, Dahlberg returned to the United States and wrote a number of other works that reflected his early life, including From Flushing to Calvary (1932) and Those Who Perish (1934).
For a number of years, Dahlberg devoted himself to literary study. His extensive readings of the works of Dante, Shakespeare, Thoreau, and many others, resulted in a writing style quite different from the social realism that characterized his earlier writing. Dahlberg's new style, one rich in biblical and classical allusions, first appeared in Do These Bones Live (1941), a collection of essays on American Literature.
During most of the 1940s and 1950s, Dahlberg wrote little, but during the 1960s and 1970s, he became quite prolific and further refined his unique style through the publication of poetry, autobiographical works, fiction, and criticism. Dahlberg died in Santa Barbara, California in 1977.
Access
The collection is open for research.
Dahlberg, Edward, 1900-1977.; American literatue--20th century
- Series I. PERSONAL
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains materials from Dahlberg's personal life, including medical records, bankbooks, and passports.
  - Bankbooks, 1948-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Booksellers: letter, invoices, 1958-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Complaint responses: letters to Dahlberg regarding filed complaints, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Disability claims: letters, forms, 1954-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Divorce materials: divorce certificate, letters from the Veterans Association, 1949-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Income tax: income tax returns and related documents, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Insurance claims: claims for lost and damaged books, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Inventory notebooks: spiral-bound notebooks with inventory of items (mostly books) to be shipped from Dublin to New York City., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Jewish Orphans Home: letters, flyers, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Medical documents: statements, letters, 1957-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorial Record: commemorative prayer book from Dahlberg's funeral, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous documents: clippings, flyers, social security statement, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Passports, 1953-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Relocation: letters, receipts, leases, 1958-1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II. CORRESPONDENCE
  This series contains incoming and some outgoing correspondence. Outgoing letters from Dahlberg have been specifically noted in the folder descriptions. Dahlberg made drafts of his letters, so in many cases it is difficult to determine if a letter was actually sent. For more information on Dahlberg's letter-writing process, see Irving Rosenthal's cover note in folder 2.1. Typescripts, clippings, and other materials originally included with incoming correspondence have been retained in this series in order to preserve the context of these items.
  - Cover note: note by Irving Rosenthal explaining Dahlberg's process for writing letters, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Aaron, Daniel: letter, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Allen, Mary E.: greeting cards, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Arnold, Walter: letters, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Barnett, Anthony: letters, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Billings, Harold: letters, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Blankfort, Michael: letter, postcard, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Boyle, Kay: letter, note, 1967-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Britton, Coburn: letters, 1967-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Brown, Andreas: letter, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Brown, Francis: letter, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Brown, Garech: letters, note by Dahlberg, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Burnshaw, Stanley: typescripts of poems, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Cech, John: letters, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Corman, Cid: letter from Dahlberg, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Dahlberg, Geoffrey: letters, receipt, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Dahlberg, Joel: letters, 1967-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Dahlberg, Julia: letters, greeting cards, journal, medical records, notes, receipts, materials from Pinecrest Hospital chemical dependency program, 1966-1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Dahlberg, Rlene: letters, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - DeFanti, Charles: letters, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Dobell, Byron: letters, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Duran, Gregorio: letters, greeting cards, notes, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ellison, Nicholas: letters, telegrams, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ford, Gerald: mailgram from Dahlberg, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Haberman, Daniel: letter, greeting card, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Howe, Fanny: letters, typescripts of poems, short prose piece on Dahlberg, 1964-1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Johns, Richard: draft of letter from Dahlberg, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Jovanovich, William: letters, mostly regarding the publication of Dahlberg's books by Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, inc.; includes booklet by Jovanovich; letter from William Saroyan to Jovanovich., 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Kennedy, Robert F.: copy of letter from Dahlberg, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Lipton, Victor: letter from Dahlberg, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - MacDonald, Nadine: letters, photographs, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - MacShane, Frank: draft of letter from Dahlberg, clippings, typescript, 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Maloff, Saul: copy of clipping, Dahlberg's notes on Maloff's review of Festschrift (the Dahlberg issue), 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Matthews, Jack: letters, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Menn, Thorpe: letters, clippings, greeting card, notes, 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Moramarco, Fred: letter, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Olson, Charles: letter, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - O'Rourke, William: letters, typescripts, 1967-1977 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Pearson, Drew: letter from Dahlberg, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Perkins, Michael: postcard, greeting card, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Perret, Juditte: letters, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Ransom, Harry: letter from Dahlberg, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Read, Herbert: letter from Dahlberg, clipping, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ridge, George Ross: typescript, The Black Beatitudes, dedicated to Dahlberg, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Rodman, Selden: letter, 1971 (Box 3, Box 7)
  - Rohman, Richard: letters, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Rozen, Susan W.: letters, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ryan, William: letters, letter by Dahlberg, 1967-1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Skir, Leo: letter, clipping of journal article, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sorrentino, Gilbert: letters, draft of letter from Dahlberg, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Tate, Allen and Isabella Gardner: telegram, letters, letter from Dahlberg, 1959-1977 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Wallace, George: letter from Dahlberg, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Williams, Jonathan: telegram, letters, distribution list for Festschrift, typescript for Williams' tribute to Dahlberg, "The Dead are made to Eat Asphodels", 1963-1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Wilson, Edmund: letter, no date (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Woolf, Douglas: letters, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence: telegram, letter, note, Circa 1950-1961 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series III. PROFFESIONAL
  This series contains materials specifically related to Dahlberg's work as a writer and teacher. It includes typescripts, notes, proofs for specific books, miscellaneous notes listed chronologically, and correspondence with publishers and other professional contacts.
  - Abel's Confession: typescript, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Art foundations: letters, telegram, grant application, 1961-1971 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Authors Guild: letters, 1964-1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Biographical notes: drafts of short biographical notes for book jackets, etc., 1967-1975 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - The Carnal Myth: typescripts for chapters 1, 2, 6, 9, and unpublished section, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Community College: letters, memos, student exams, and other materials from Dahlberg's time as a community college instructor in New York, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - The Confessions of Edward Dahlberg: notes, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - The Confessions of Edward Dahlberg: annotated typescript of unpublished section, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Creative Artists Public Service Program: letters, 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Crowell anthology, Bottom Dogs; From Flushing to Calvary; Those who Perish: and Hitherto Unpublished and Uncollected Works (3.28-4.3.), 1976
    Note
    Typescripts listed below are usually annotated copies of previously published work; oversized proofs moved to flat box 5.
    - Crowell anthology: copy of preface and introduction with annotations by Dahlberg, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Crowell anthology: annotated typescripts; includes Bitch Goddess., 1976 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Crowell anthology: annotated typescripts; includes Bottom Dogs., 1976 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Crowell anthology: annotated typescripts; includes chapter 13 from Bottom Dogs., 1976 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Crowell anthology: annotated typescripts; includes The Confessions of Edward Dahlberg., 1976 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Crowell anthology: annotated typescripts; includes From Flushing to Calvary., 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Crowell anthology: annotated typescripts; includes Those who Perish., 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Crowell anthology: master pages, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Crowell anthology: annotated galley proof, 1976 (Flat-box 5, Folder 1)
    - Crowell anthology: annotated page proof, 1976 (Flat-box 5, Folder 2)
    - Crowell anthology: corrected page proof, 1976 (Flat-box 5, Folder 3)
  - Death camp survivor stories: copies of two typescripts by Holocaust survivor with annotations by Dahlberg, Circa 1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fans and students: letters from fans and students; includes postcards, greeting cards, booklet., Circa 1968-1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Festschrift: proof for piece published in Festschrift, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - House of El Dieff: letters and telegram from manuscript dealer regarding the sale of Dahlberg's papers to the University of Texas, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Invoices: invoices from Dahlberg's publishers, 1967-1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Job references: reference letters for Dahlberg, flyers, description of Writer-in-Residence position, 1952-1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Leafless American: broadside of Dahlberg poem, inscribed to Dahlberg by Harold and Bernice Billings, 1968 (Flat-box 5, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous publishers: letters from publishers; includes contract., 1958-1975 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - New Directions: letters, postcards, 1960-1974 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - New York Review of Books: letters to the editor, clippings, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Notes: typed and holograph notes for miscellaneous works, organized chronologically by Irving Rosenthal (4.13-9.1.), 1965-1976
    - Notes, Circa 1965-1975 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Notes, July, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Notes, March, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Notes, July, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Notes, August-September, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Notes, Circa 1969-1975 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    - Notes, August-December, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Notes, January-March, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Notes, March-July, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Notes, July-December, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Notes, January-April, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - Notes, May-December, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Notes, June-July, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Notes, April-May, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Notes, June-July, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 4-6)
    - Notes, Circa 1975 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Notes, January, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Notes: removed from books in Dahlberg's library during processing, no date (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Olive of Minerva; or, The Comedy of a Cuckold, notes: typed and holograph notes organized chronologically by Irving Rosenthal (9.3-11.2.), Circa 1964-1979
    - Olive of Minerva, notes, Circa 1964-1979 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
    - Olive of Minerva, notes, January, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Olive of Minerva, notes, December-March, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Olive of Minerva, notes, January-April, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
    - Olive of Minerva, notes, May-October, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Olive of Minerva, notes in literary sequence, September-October, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Olive of Minerva, notes, January-October, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
    - Olive of Minerva, notes, November-December, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
    - Olive of Minerva, notes, August-December, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Olive of Minerva; or, The Comedy of a Cuckold (11.3-13.1.), 1973-1976
    - Olive of Minerva: sample proof of title page, chapter, and page specifications with corrections by Dahlberg, June 19, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Olive of Minerva: miscellaneous annotated typescripts, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Olive of Minerva: front matter proof; includes publisher's corrections., 1974 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Olive of Minerva: typescript; first revision with annotations by Dahlberg., 1975 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Olive of Minerva: typescript; second revision with extensive annotations by Dahlberg., 1975 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Olive of Minerva: typescript; third revision with minor edits., 1975 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Olive of Minerva: typescript; final revision with editor's and printer's notes., 1975 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Olive of Minerva: galley proof; includes annotated typescript inserts., 1975 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Olive of Minerva: page proof, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Olive of Minerva: Dahlberg's notes on page proof corrections, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Olive of Minerva: trial dummy signed by Dahlberg, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Olive of Minerva: book published by Thomas Y. Crowell Company; contains Dahlberg's annotations; also Julia Dahlberg's distribution list., 1976 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Olive of Minerva: proof for excerpts published in Prose, 1973 (Flat-box 13, Folder 1)
  - Sorrows of Priapus: annotated typescript for new edition, Circa 1973 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Three Tales of Love: title page mock ups, no date (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Weybright and Talley, inc.: letters, draft of letter from Dahlberg, copy of annotated proof for "Quotations from Edward Dahlberg's latest work: The Carnal Myth", 1968-1972 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Series IV. PHOTOGRAPHS
  This series contains photographs taken of Dahlberg between 1960 and 1977. It also includes photographs taken by Julia Dahlberg of friends and family after Dahlberg's death.
  - Photographs of Dahlberg: includes negatives, clipping, a few earlier photographs, one may possibly be Dahlberg's father, Circa 1960-1970 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Dahlberg: 8" x 10" black and white portraits, Circa 1970 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Dahlberg, Julia: photographs taken by Julia; includes note by Irving Rosenthal and negatives., 1978-1991 (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
- Series V. CLIPPINGS
  This series contains clippings of book reviews and other articles related to Dahlberg organized chronologically.
  - Clippings, 1961-1967 (Flat-box 15, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1968-1970 (Flat-box 15, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1971-1974 (Flat-box 15, Folder 3)